# MUSTAFA BILAL TAHIR

Phone Number: (206) 295-3642 Email Address: <a href="mailto:bilal.tahir89@gmail.com">bilal.tahir89@gmail.com</a> Email Address: <a href="mailto:bilal.tahir89@gmail.com">bilal.tahir89@gmail.com</a> Github Profile: <a href="https://github.com/btahir">https://github.com/btahir</a>

## **SUMMARY**

I have a passion for finding meaning in data and want to leverage my skill set and experience to transition into a Data Analytics role. I believe I have a great base of skills and experience through my education and work, and the right learning focused attitude to excel in this role.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

### Towers Watson (Actuarial Consultancy Firm) Senior Actuarial Analyst

Seattle, Washington October 2013 – Present

- Promoted to Senior Actuarial Analyst in October 2013 based on performance and feedback
- Took on a more independent and project management oriented role on client teams
- Successfully led projects from start to finish delivering high quality deliverables to clients on time and within budget
- Coordinated between team members, reviewed work and gave instructions on work processes to junior analysts

Actuarial Analyst August 2011 – September 2013

- Wrangled, queried, manipulated and analyzed data using a variety of tools (Excel, Access, company software (VBA based) etc.) for actuarial valuation work.
- Ran multi-billion dollar actuarial valuations under different funding and accounting standards; and compiled results into final deliverables such as reports and exhibits for clients
- Performed extensive data analysis on ad-hoc projects such as pension plan design, experience studies, cost analysis and pricing etc. to help clients optimize their pension plans.
- Worked and produced high quality deliverables on a variety of projects such as Pension Benefit Calculations, Non-Discrimination Testing, Cost sensitivity analysis, Projections/ Forecasting, Government filings, Bulk Lump Sum valuations and client presentations
- Maintained, debugged, and programmed Database system used to perform valuations and benefit calculations

# Nauman Associates (Actuarial Consultancy Firm)

Lahore, Pakistan

Intern

June 2010 – August 2010

- Prepared data for actuarial valuations and reviewed accounting disclosures and final valuation reports as per international accounting standard 19 (IAS 19) that were to be sent to clients
- Researched the life insurance market of Sri Lanka, conducted financial analysis of 3 of the biggest 5 insurance companies, and explored and analyzed the various life insurance products offered by them in order to provide ideas for improving Pakistan's insurance industry

Residential Education Oberlin College
Resident Assistant (RA) August 2008 – December 2009

• Supervised 33 residents to keep a safe and productive environment inside residence halls and maintain a strong and healthy community

# **EDUCATION**

**Bachelor of Arts** (Economics, Mathematics)

May 2011

Oberlin College, Oberlin, Ohio

Actuarial Exams: Passed exams P (9), FM (8), MFE (8) and MLC (8)

**Certifications:** Data Analyst Nanodegree at Udacity. Languages: Python, R, SQL, MongoDB. Topics: data wrangling, statistical analysis, machine learning (in progress)

#### **PROJECTS**

### **Analyzing the New York City Subway**

February 2015

Analyzed a New York City subway data set for a given month to see if rain has any measurable impact on ridership. Used: Python (Pandas, PandaSQL, Numpy, ggplot)

### **Exploratory Data Analysis of Red Wine Quality**

March 2015

Explored and analyzed the relationship of red wine quality with different variables, using statistical analysis and resulting in using univariate, bivariate and multivariate plots. Used: R, R studio, R Markdown (to create a final HTML document), ggplot2 (to create plots)

### **SKILLS**

**Software Skills:** Actuarial Software, Java, VBA, Python, IPython, SQL, R, R Studio, Visual Fox Pro, Stata, Relius. **Languages:** Urdu (Native Fluency), Hindi (Native Fluency), Arabic (Writing Proficiency).